Preetam Kumar

Email: pritam.c73@gmail.com
Address: Deffodil Heights, Greater Noida,

DOB: 3rd Feb 1995 201009, UP **Mob:** +91 7982770608 **Language:** English & Hindi

Objective

A competent professional and creative team player with around 4 years of IT experience who specializes in planning, designing and maintaining software programs. Employs my skills in coding and software design to meet the organization's requirements.

Professional experiences

Sr. Software Engineer, HCL Technologies, Noida Feb 2022 – Jan 2023

- Building a ServiceNow custom application to perform security scanning operations for the bank. Perform planning, core configuration, development along with 3rd party integrations.
- Managing client scripts, UI policies, UI actions, business rules, Event notifications.
- Managing Data with tables, CMDB, Update Sets import- export, Dashboards, Reports, Configurations between two instances & REST APIs.
- Identified and implemented new processes to improve the reliability, repeatability and efficiency.
- Contributing and taking part of software and architectural development activities.

JAVA Developer, BR Softech Pvt. Ltd, Jaipur May 2019 – 31st Jan 2022

- Built, maintained, enhanced and scaled infrastructure for multiple web applications based on ecommerce, payments, ERP System.
- Worked with Java J2EE technologies with spring framework (spring boot & micro services) to build web applications, REST APIs & more as per the requirements.
- Worked with spring security to implement both authentication and authorization for the application.
- Worked with JPA Hibernate to reduce lines of code by maintaining object-table mapping itself.
- Created dynamic web pages using HTML 5, Thymeleaf and handle all the request/response using jQuery,
 JavaScript & Ajax.
- Integrated 3rd Party APIs to add the functionalities of SMS, EMAIL and Tracking management.
- Worked with Rest APIs to provide the data with secure format to application team using JWT.
- Worked on SQL & NoSQL (MySQL, Oracle & Couchbase) Databases.
- Used debugging skills to improve the quality of code and improve application performance
- Used Spring Logger for file logging of every request/response.
- Worked with GitHub/Bit bucket Git Repository to collaborate and manage the source code.
- Worked in a team of developers, designers, testers and other IT personnel to meet team goals.

Software Trainee Engineer, Medimojo Pvt Ltd, New Delhi Jan 2019 – April 2019

- Worked on MySQL (primary) database to manage the huge amounts of data for core products of the company.
- Wrote some importers for multiple partners for data integration.
- Worked on front end using HTML5, CSS and JavaScript for the web applications.
- Gained practical experience in working with a small team of a start-up.
- Familiarity with XML/Web Services technologies (REST).

Projects

Security Assessments Scanning Application

Technologies Used – ServiceNow Platform, Qualys.

Role - Developer

Team Size - 06

Project Period - April 2022 - January 2023

Chat Server System

Technologies Used – Web Socket, Netty, Spring,

Hibernate, JPA, Redis Cache.

Database - MySQL

Role – Developer, Provide REST APIs to Unity team.

Team Size - 02

Project Period - May 2021 - 31st Jan 2022

POS Web & Application System

Technologies Used – Spring Boot, JPA, Hibernate, HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, JavaScript, Ajax, jQuery, Redis Cache.

Database - MySQL

Role – Full-stack Developer, Provided APIs.

Team Size – 04

Project Period – Sept 2020 – May 2021

Online Examination System

Technologies Used - Spring Boot, JPA, Hibernate, REST API

Database - Couchbase Server

Server – Tomcat 9

Role - Developer, Provided REST APIs to front-end team

Team Size - 02

Project Period – Jan 2020 – Aug 2020

E-Commerce Web & Application

Technologies Used – Spring Boot, JPA, Hibernate, HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, JavaScript, Ajax, jQuery.

Database - MySQL

Role – Full-stack Developer, Provided APIs.

Team Size - 04

Project Period - Aug 2019 - Dec 2019

Web Application (Learning Management System)

Technologies Used – Spring Boot, JPA, Hibernate, HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, JavaScript, Ajax, jQuery.

Database – MySQL

Role – Full-stack Developer

Team Size - 03

Project Period - May 2019 - August 2019

Technical Skills

- Java (J2SE & J2EE)
- Microservices
- Spring Framework / Spring Boot
- Restful Web Services
- JPA & Hibernate
- Jenkins
- ServiceNow Platform

- HTML 5, JavaScript, jQuery & Ajax
- MySQL & Oracle Database
- Couchbase Server, Mongo DB
- Tomcat Server
- IntelliJ & Eclipse IDE
- Windows/Linux
- GIT & Maven

Education

Computer Science & Engineering

BIJU Patnaik University of Technology, Odisha

Intermediate

+2KNSM Inter School, BSEB Patna, Bihar

Preetam Kumar

Date: 10th January 2023